We ask a lot of questions
about our diet.
What’s the right way to
treat a chronic illness?
Fight off a virus,
lose weight?
The problem is, we get
a lot of different answers.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
People spend lots of time and effort
trying to keep their ears free of ear wax.
It may not surprise you to know that
some methods work better than others.
Ear candles
(also known as ear cones)
are promoted as a low cost,
effective treatment for earwax.
They're hollow tubes of fabric
impregnated with paraffin
or beeswax.
One end is placed
in the entrance
to the ear canal
and the other end is lit.
After 15 minutes or so,
the flame is extinguished,
and a brownish waxy substance
can be seen
within the remaining stub.
This is claimed to be earwax
drawn out by some sort of
vacuum "chimney effect."
But the same residue
(presumably
from the burning wax smoke)
appears if you burn it alone
outside the ear.
Researchers actually took
the additional step
of running
used ear candle stubs
through a mass spectrometer,
and indeed,
no evidence of earwax
was found.
Not surprisingly, perhaps,
since tympanometric
measurements showed
no signs of negative
"chimney effect" pressure
at any point.
Not to be dissuaded,
proponents suggest
that while no earwax
may be drawn out that day,
the candling process
at least heats up
and melts the earwax,
which then comes out naturally
over the next few days.
But Health Canada measured
the air temperature
at the ear end
of the burning candle,
and the highest temperature
reached
was only 72 degrees Fahrenheit,
well below body temperature.
Though the purported theories
were found to be
"implausible
and demonstrably wrong,"
the only way to really tell
if it works
is to examine the wax buildup
in people
before and after ear candling.
Photographs
inside the ear canal
were taken before and after
ear candling.
Not only was no wax removed,
but in some of the ear canals
candle wax was deposited.
So they ended up worse
than they were before,
not to mention
the recorded complications,
including ear burns,
complete candle wax blockage
of ear canals,
eardrum perforation,
infection,
and setting people's hair
on fire.
Researchers concluded,
"Ear candles have no benefit
in the management of earwax
and may result
in serious injury."
Ear candles appear
to be a triumph
of ignorance over science.
So, what is effective
for getting rid of earwax?
I'll cover that, next...
One of the most common
reversible causes
of hearing loss
is earwax buildup.
Earwax is normal,
and if it isn't causing symptoms
should be left alone.
It doesn't start interfering
with hearing acuity
until it clogs off
at least 80 percent
of the ear canal.
Ironically, hearing aids
are a risk factor
for excessive earwax,
as are anything else you put
in your ear, like ear plugs,
since that stimulates
the earwax glands.
For further irony,
so may cotton-tipped swabs
that as many as two-thirds
of people use
to clean their ears.
You may think
you're making things better
by swabbing out your ears,
but you may actually be
making them worse.
Simply removing protective wax
can leave your ear canals dry,
itchy, and achy
or even lead to "Q-tip otalgia,"
a term coined
to refer to an ear pain syndrome
caused by cotton-tipped swabs.
You shouldn't need to clean
your ear canals at all
because the wax should make
its way out on its own.
That's right.
Ears are self-cleaning.
The lining of your ear canal
grows outward
from your eardrum,
so secreted earwax
and any dirt that's trapped
is eventually conveyor belted
out of the ear.
However, this self-cleaning
mechanism can fail
in 1 in 20 younger adults
and in as many
as 1 in 3 older adults
and lead to excessive or
impacted earwax accumulation,
though they may not
even know it.
Seventy percent
of those surveyed
who had both ears
completely blocked with wax
thought their hearing was good.
But when their ears
were cleared,
they were suddenly able
to hear better.
Clearing out impacted wax
can also improve symptoms
of ear irritation, pressure,
and fullness.
So, what's the best way
to do it?
Q-tips are a no-no.
Pushing anything
into the ear canal
can end up making things worse
by impacting wax
even deeper into the ear
or traumatizing the canal,
resulting in abrasions,
infections,
or even, rarely,
eardrum perforation.
There's even a case report
of a cotton swab causing
a brain abscess
and fatal meningitis,
though the presence
of wood splinters
suggests the tip had broken off
inside the ear.
Cotton swab packaging
already cautions users
against ear canal insertion,
but perhaps warning labels
should be made even clearer,
wrote one clinical
medical officer:
"do not go near the ear hole
or avoid the ear altogether."
What about those ear drops
sold for wax removal?
There are about a dozen
different marketed formulations
on the market,
none of which appears to work
any better than any other,
or even compared to saline
(which is just salt water)
or plain tap water.
But five days of treatment
does clear earwax
in about 1 in 5 cases
compared to only 1 in 20
that clear up on their own
within that time.
At the very least,
those ear drops
may be able to soften wax
before bulb syringe irrigation.
Irrigation
(also called ear syringing)
involves flushing out the wax
with a low-pressure jet of warm
(body temperature) water.
It works up to 70 to 90 percent
of the time,
and if it doesn't,
clinicians have fancy devices
to manually remove the wax
under direct observation.
The irrigation can be tried
at home, though.
Researchers randomized
to use a bulb at home
had about a 50 percent
success rate
in clearing their obstruction,
and armed with this knowledge
were significantly less likely
to subsequently require
in-office irrigation.
Significant complications
only happen
in approximately
1 in 1000 irrigations.
You should not use
an oral water jet.
There are papers with names like
"Catastrophic Otologic Injury From Oral Jet
Irrigation of the External Auditory Canal."
Even at one-third power,
Waterpiks were shown to be able
to perforate the eardrums
of fresh cadavers.
Those who insist
on violating this advice
should at the very least
use the lowest setting,
use a tip
with multiple orifices,
and make sure the water stream
is directed
only against the walls
of the ear canal,
never straight back
towards the eardrum.
But really, just don't do it.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you hear about any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
I also wrote a
mini book on Ozempic.
Available in softcover,
e-book, and audio versions.
Check it out on NutritionFacts.org.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.